DIPESH JAIN

IT Infrastructure Specialist

Email: ddipeshj@gmail.com, Mob: 9650990997

SUMMARY

16+ years of intensive work experience with prestigious Indian government / private organizations in different IT verticals such as Cloud Computing, IT Security, IT Network Administration, Data Centre Management, ERP implementation (PeopleSoft and SAP), Software Development, Database Administration, Video Conferencing, CCTV Camera, Telephone Exchange, IT Procurements, Contracts, Rolling plans, Annual budgets, Framing of IT Policy, Conducting IS Audits, Statutory Compliances etc.

QUALIFICATIONS

- Master of Technology in Computing Systems and Infrastructure from BITS Pilani(pursuing).
- Bachelor of Technology in Computer Science & Engineering with 71% (1st Division) in 2004 from U.P Technical University, Lucknow.
- Secured 87 % Marks in 12th Std.
- Secured 81 % Marks in 10th Std.

KEY ACCOMPLISHMENTS

- Received Appreciation letter from CEO, NSPCL for implementation of SAP / ERP in record time
 of nine and half months in NSPCL.
- Secured 99.02 %, AIR-262 in GATE (Computer Sc.) in year 2005.
- I received Certificate of Merit from CBSE for reasons of outstanding academic performance and for being among top 0.1 percent of the successful candidates of All India Secondary School Examination 1998 in Mathematics.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Period : 12.12.2018 – till date 11.12.2018

Project: A premier Govt Financial Organization (Name Confidential)

Department: Information Technology **Designation**: E6/ Chief Manager

JOB RESPONSIBILITIES

A. Disaster recovery Site on Cloud

- 1. **Disaster Recovery:** Continuous replication of data from DR to DRC, Online backups through Sybase Client, Offline backups through Tape Library Management (HP), DC-DR Mock drills, Optimal network configuration and DNS Management for seamless DC-DR swap with least downtime.
- 2. **Cloud Hosting:** Hosting and Management of software applications like SRM portal, ESS portal, PFC Website, etc. on Cloud with DNS Zone Management, NATing, CPanel, etc.

B. IT Security

- 1. **Network Security:** Centralised Firewall Management for all NSPCL locations, configuration of hosts, host groups, routing, access control policies, routing, web filtering etc. (Fortinet-600c & Cyberoam-CR1000ING-XP).
- 2. **Endpoint Security:** Antivirus Management, Patch updation, Intrusion prevention and detection through past logs and events, Configuration of Anti-Spam gateways and spam monitoring.
- 3. **Secure Connectivity through SSL**: Configuration of SSL digital server certificates on servers to provide their secure https access to NSPCL users over internet, Configuration of SSL VPN for

- connecting users to critical applications over internet with security controls based on authenticated user logins, IP address, MAC address, limited time based slots etc.
- 4. **IT Security Policy and Audit**: Framing of IT security policies and scoping of IT security audit as per industry standards.

C. IT Network Administration

- 1. **WAN Connectivity**: Designing of NSPCL's Wide Area Networks to cater both NSPCL and NTPC networks, Grouping and Isolation of MPLS links through BGP protocols to avoid overlapping of networks, Configuration of routers with static routing, QOS, Port aggregation, Ensuring availability of WAN Connectivity (primary and secondary) at all sites with regular monitoring through different network tools (PRTG).
- 2. **LAN Connectivity:** Network Design Layout at Data Centre, NSPCL-HQ and sites with optimum sub mask, Configuration of L3 switches with VLAN etc.
- 3. **Internet Facility**: Providing Internet for official use through Internet Lease Lines with web filtering and web traffic usage monitoring through proxy server.

D. Server Administration

- 1. Planning, Procurement, Installation, Commissioning, Maintenance, Administration and Monitoring of Unix servers, Windows Blade Servers, Virtual Machines hosted on these physical servers. Planning of BOQ as per SAPS recommended by SAP. Augmentation of Servers before reaching utilisation limit.
- 2. Installation, Configuration and Updation of Windows Server 2008 / 2012, Linux-Ubuntu-14.x / 16.x, UNIX HP-UX.

E. Storage and Backup Administration

- 1. Planning, Procurement, Installation, Commissioning, Maintenance, Administration and Monitoring of SAN / NAS Storage Augmentation of Storage before reaching utilisation limit.
- 2. Configuration of logical drives and assignment of SAN Storage (HP 3PAR) pools to different Servers.

F. Planning & Budgeting

Framing of Annual / 3-Year IT Rolling Plans, Annual Budgets and Annual Utilisation as per IT requirements of the organisation.

Period : 01.11.2013 – 11.12.2018

Project: NSPCL (NTPC- SAIL Joint Venture Company)

Department: IT/ERP/Communication **Designation**: E5/Manager, NTPC Ltd

JOB RESPONSIBILITIES

G. IT Network Administration and IT Security

- 1. **WAN Connectivity**: Designing of NSPCL's Wide Area Networks to cater both NSPCL and NTPC networks, Grouping and Isolation of MPLS links through BGP protocols to avoid overlapping of networks, Configuration of routers with static routing, QOS, Port aggregation, Ensuring availability of WAN Connectivity (primary and secondary) at all sites with regular monitoring through different network tools (PRTG).
- 2. **LAN Connectivity:** Network Design Layout at Data Centre, NSPCL-HQ and sites with optimum sub mask, Configuration of L3 switches with VLAN etc.
- 3. **Internet Facility**: Providing Internet for official use through Internet Lease Lines with web filtering and web traffic usage monitoring through proxy server.

- 4. **Network Security:** Centralised Firewall Management for all NSPCL locations, configuration of hosts, host groups, routing, access control policies, routing, web filtering etc. (Fortinet-600c & Cyberoam-CR1000ING-XP).
- 5. **Endpoint Security:** Antivirus Management, Patch updation, Intrusion prevention and detection through past logs and events, Configuration of Anti-Spam gateways and spam monitoring.
- 6. **Secure Connectivity through SSL**: Configuration of SSL digital server certificates on servers to provide their secure https access to NSPCL users over internet, Configuration of SSL VPN for connecting users to critical applications over internet with security controls based on authenticated user logins, IP address, MAC address, limited time based slots etc.
- 7. **IT Security Policy and Audit**: Framing of IT security policies and scoping of IT security audit as per industry standards.

H. IT Infrastructure Administration and Data Centre Management

- 1. **IT and ERP Infrastructure**: Planning, Procurement, Installation, Commissioning, Maintenance, Administration and Monitoring of critical equipments installed at Data Centre (DC) and Disaster Recovery Centre (DRC). These equipments include High end Unix servers, Windows Blade Servers, Virtual Machines hosted on these physical servers. Planning of BOQ as per SAPS recommended by SAP. Augmentation of Servers and Storage before reaching utilisation limit.
- 2. **Capacity Planning:** Making 3-Year IT Rolling Plans, Annual Budgets and Annual Utilisation as per IT requirements of NSPCL.
- 3. **Data Centre Management:** Rack wise Power usage planning and monitoring, Environment monitoring in respect of ambient temperature and clean air. Ensuring time synchronisation of all devices through master GPS clock, Round the clock staff deployment with authenticated access to server room.
- 4. **Disaster Recovery:** Continuous replication of data from DR to DRC, Online backups through Sybase Client, Offline backups through Tape Library Management (HP), DC-DR Mock drills, Optimal network configuration and DNS Management for seamless DC-DR swap with least downtime.
- 5. **Cloud Hosting:** Hosting and Management of software applications like SRM portal, ESS portal, NSPCL Website, etc. on Cloud with DNS Zone Management, NATing, CPanel, etc.
- 6. **Operating System Administration**: Installation, Configuration and Updation of Windows Server 2008 / 2012, Linux-Ubuntu-14.x / 16.x, UNIX HP-UX.
- 7. **SAN Storage Administration (HP 3PAR):** Configuration of logical drives and assignment of Storage pools to different Servers.
- 8. **Local IT Support:** Maintenance and Support of PCs, Printers, UPS and of softwares like MS Office, Adobe Reader, Browsers etc. to users at NSPCL-CC.

I. IT Services

- 1. **NSPCL official Mail (Zimbra)**: Installation, Configuration and Maintenance of Zimbra mail server 8.x on Ubuntu 14.x for 1000 users in NSPCL.
- 2. Video Conferencing System across all NSPCL Sites (Polycom).
- 3. **Telephone Exchange**: Administration of Coral IPBX System.
- 4. **NSPCL Website:** Hosting, Maintenance and regular updation of NSPCL Website with Data such as Latest News, Announcements and uploading of Documents like Newsletters, Circulars and MOUs.

J. IT Procurement and Contract Handling

- 1. **Creation and Processing of SAP documents** related to procurement and contract handling such as Purchase Requisitions, Purchase Orders, Store Issue Vouchers (SIV), parking of Invoices, Quality Inspection etc.
- 2. **Post GST regime:** Handling of Contracts post GST and necessary contractual amendments required for invoicing and payments.

K. Software Application Development

1. **SAP ABAP Development:** MVC Web Dynpro / ALV / Smartforms / Screen Programming / ESS Applications etc.

- 2. **PHP Development:** Development of Web based softwares on core PHP 5.x, Laravel5.x, Cakephp, CMS-Wordpress / Joomla. I have developed website for Corporate Intranet, Central File Tracking System, IT Asset Management System etc.
- 3. **Database Administration:** Mysql-5.x, MS-Sql server -2008 / 2012.

4. Support for legacy IT applications like Enterprise Risk Management System, Biometric Attendance System, Material Codification system etc.

Period : 20.04.2010 - 31.10.2013

Project: Faridabad Gas Power Station, NTPC Ltd.

Department: IT/ERP/Communication **Designation**: E3/Dy. Manager, NTPC Ltd

JOB RESPONSIBILITIES

A. IT Infrastructure Administration

- 1. Administration and Maintenance of Servers Windows and Linux based
- 2. Maintenance and Support for Desktops, Printers and Peripherals.

B. Network Administration

- 1. **LAN Connectivity:** Network Design Layout according to Class of Networks, Configuration of L3 switches with VLAN.
- 2. **Providing Internet Facility** through Internet Lease Lines with web filtering and web traffic usage monitoring through proxy server.

C. Development of Local & Centralized IT applications in using PHP/MySql Web technologies:

- 1. Development of Faridabad Website with features like Photo Gallery, Birthday Application, Latest News & Circulars / Tel. Directory/ Departmental Web Administration / Online complaints/ Suggestions etc.
- 2. SMS Alert System HR Alerts/ Daily Plant Parameters etc.
- 3. FGPS Telephone Directory.
- 4. FGPS Network Real Time Monitoring Software.
- 5. Intelligence Bureau Audit Software for CC-IT.

D. SAP-ABAP Development:

- 1. I underwent SAP -ABAP Basic and advanced trainings organized by NTPC -SAP Dept.
- 2. I developed various SAP modules in 2-Tier and 3-Tier architecture using various ABAP features like MVC programming, Screen Programming, ALV reports, Smart-Forms in functional domains of HR, MM & OS

E. IT Services

- 1. Video and Audio Conferencing, CCTV cameras, Telephone Exchange etc.
- 2. Implementation of Active Directory Services.
- 3. Administration of Lotus Domino and Zimbra Mail Services.
- 4. Management of Plant Information (PI) Server which provides real time parameters of plant equipment through PI tags and various reports were developed using these PI tags.
- 5. Support for legacy IT Applications like Labor and Material Gate Pass systems, Hospital Management Systems etc.

Period : 06.09.2004 - 19.04.2010

Project: Corporate Centre – NTPC Ltd., Scope Complex, New Delhi

Department: HR-IT

Designation: E2/Engineer, NTPC Ltd

JOB RESPONSIBILITIES

- 1. **PeopleSoft-HRMS Implementation:** Nodal Manager for implementing PeopleSoft –ERP in various NTPC sites like CC-Delhi, EOC-Noida, BTPC-Badarpur, FGPS-Faridabad, Unchahar (UP), Auraiya (UP), Tanda (UP), Koldam(HP) etc.
- 2. **Designing of Business process maps** for PeopleSoft-HRMS modules such as Payroll, Time & Attendance, LTC, Reimbursements, Advances, PMS, Training, etc. with consultation with HR process owners.
- 3. **Database Administration:** Installation / Configuration and Administration of Oracle 9i /10g DBMS with data backups and migration to other DBMS.
- 4. **PL/SQL Report development in SQR** (Structured Query Reports): Development of various SQR reports like manpower data, seniority lists, bio data etc. from oracle database.
- 5. **Programming in People code:** development & customization of PeopleSoft-HRMS modules in application designer (development framework of people soft) and other PeopleTools.
- 6. **PeopleSoft End user support:** Providing the process owners and end users the training, hand holding and daily reports in different modules. Analysis and mining of data into customized data lists as per requirement of NTPC management.

PERSONAL DETAILS

Father's Name: Anil Kumar Jain

Birth year : 1982 Marital Status : Married Gender : Male

Hobbies: Photography, Socializing, Listening Music.

Location : Noida/Delhi

DECLARATION

I, hereby declare that the above written particulars are true to the best of my knowledge & belief.

Dipesh Jain